This is the bigger picture of what webpack is and does, let's understand how it works behind the scenes
Bu, webpack'in ne olduunun ve yaptklarnn daha byk resmidr, tm ina i akmz yrten ok nemli bir
since it is such a crucial tool handling our whole build workflow. Behind the scenes, webpack has four
ara olduu iin, perde arkasnda nasl altn anlayalm. Perde arkasnda, webpack'in drt nemli zellii var,
important things, four important features,
drt nemli zellii var, her zaman en az
it always needs at least one entry point,
bir giri noktasna ihtiya var, birden
you can have multiple ones.
fazla tane olabilir.
This could be our app.js file, our root javascript file which mounts our react application to
Bu bizim app olabilir. js dosyas, bizim tepkisizlik uygulamamzn tepkisini uygulayan dom'a,
the dom, which calls react dom render for example, it needs this file since it then analyzes the dependencies
bizim javascript dosyasn balar, rnein bu dosyaya ihtiya duyar, nk bu dosyann bamlln analiz eder,
of this file and the root entry file will have a dependency to another file which then in turn has
nk bu dosyann bamllklarn analiz eder ve kk giri dosyas baka bir dosyaya baml
more dependencies, so webpack can build up a dependency graph starting with that root entry file
olur. Daha sonra srayla daha fazla bamllk vardr, bu yzden webpack, bu kk giri
so it can understand which files make up our application
dosyasyla balayan bir bamllk grafii oluturabilir, bylece giri
if we give it our entry file. It then analyzes all the dependencies and bundles them together into an
dosyamz verirsek hangi dosyalarn uygulamanz oluturduunu anlayabilir. Daha sonra tm bamllklar analiz eder ve
output
bunlar
we specify it like a bundle.js file in a dist folder, we specify the file name and where it should go.
bir demet gibi belirttiimiz bir ktya birletirir. js dosyas bir klasrde, dosya adn ve nereye gitmesi gerektiini belirtiriz.
And there it will put all these dependencies into that file, correctly ordered and in one concatenated
Ve orada tm bamllklar bu dosyaya, doru srayla ve birletirilmi
output file.
kt dosyasna koyacaz.
This is the core functionality but as I said it's more than that,
Bu temel ilevselliktir, ancak daha fazlas olduunu sylediim
in-between, there are two other important features we can utilize.
gibi, aralarnda kullanabileceimiz iki nemli zellik daha var.
For one there are so-called loaders, loaders are applied on a per file level so we can for example say
Bunlardan biri ykleyiciler olarak adlandrlr, ykleyiciler her dosya dzeyinde uygulanr, bylece rnein
all javascript files should get handled by loaderX, all css files should get handled by loaderY,
tm javascript dosyalarnn loaderX tarafndan ele alnmas gerektiini syleyebiliriz, tm css dosyalar
babel-loader and css-loader are two popular examples which get used in a lot of projects, so
loaderY tarafndan ele almal, babel-loader ve css-loader iki Birok projede kullanlan popler rnekler,
loaders are file dependent or apply file dependent transformations.
bu nedenle ykleyiciler dosyaya baml veya dosyaya bal dnmler uygular.
We also then have plugins where loaders are applied on a per file basis, plug
Ayrca, ykleyicilerin dosya baznda uyguland eklentileri de vardr, bunun yerine,
instead take the concatenated files, so the bundle but before it's written to the output.
birletirilen dosyalar aldk, bylece paket ancak ktya yazlmadan nce.
Here we can apply some general transformations or optimizations like uglify,
Burada irkinlik gibi baz genel dnmleri veya optimizasyonlar uygulayabiliriz, bu yzden
so this is on a global level and happens after the loaders did their job.
bu kresel bir seviyededir ve ykleyiciler ilerini yaptktan sonra gerekleir.
This is how webpack works, what it does behind the scenes
Bu, web paketinin nasl altn, sahnelerin arkasnda
and this is all set up in a webpack configuration file which we will set up together in this
ne yaptklarn ve bu, bu modlde birlikte oluturacamz bir web paketi
module.
yaplandrma dosyasnda kurulduudur.
So without further ado let's dive into building our own project setup.
Yani daha fazla ado olmadan kendi proje kurulumumuzu kurmaya balayalm.